<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Mary-Le-Bow to the Societies for Reformation of Manners, June 28, 1697 / by John Russell.</title>
            <author>Russell, John, fl. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09390876</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09390876</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42952</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57934)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42952)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1315:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Mary-Le-Bow to the Societies for Reformation of Manners, June 28, 1697 / by John Russell.</title>
                  <author>Russell, John, fl. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Darby for R. Mount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke IX, 62 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42952:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42952:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at St. <hi>Mary-Le-Bow,</hi> TO THE <hi>SOCIETIES</hi> FOR Reformation of Manners, <hi>June</hi> 28. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSELL,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Wappin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Darby,</hi> for <hi>R. Mount</hi> at the Poſtern on <hi>Tower-hill.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42952:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42952:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HE that will look over the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the moſt famous King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Governments of the World, will find that they have been rais'd and carried on to their moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted Heights, (altho eſtrang'd to the Knowledg and Worſhip of the True God) by the Rules and Practices of Moral Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: And that when the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Monarchies fell to decay, it was Luxury and Vice that open'd the Door to let in that Ruin which tranſplanted the <hi>Scepter from one Kingdom to another People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as long as they kept to their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Vertue, which laid the Foundation, and alſo built up the Edifice of their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42952:3"/>Strength and Grandeur; they maintain'd their Power, they continu'd their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: but as ſoon as they grew looſe and vicious, when Bribery and Corruption, Softneſs and Flattery ſeiz'd upon the Court, and Debauchery and Fraud, and contempt of Religion <hi>(altho a falſe one)</hi> had infected the People, they quickly grew ripe for thoſe Judgments which ſwept them into that Pit of Deſtruction, which their Immoralities had been digging as the Grave of their dying Glory and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>And tho I do not affirm that <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is founded on Grace;</hi> yet I aſſert, <hi>That all flouriſhing Kingdoms are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by Vertue:</hi> And that what People ſoever depart from that, they cut down the Props, and remove the Pillars that ſupport their own Strength and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity. And this is not only hiſtorically true, in reſpect of the Ages that are paſt and gone, but actually ſo in reſpect of our ſelves, and the very Age and Day in which we live: and it's not only ſo, in reſpect of the Nature of Vertue, which gives Men
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42952:3"/>a noble and elevated Mind, carries them thrô the greateſt Difficulties, and by Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and Honeſty muſt neceſſarily cauſe the Sun of Proſperity to ſhine upon them: And on the other ſide, in reſpect of the Nature of Vice, which enervates and ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens thoſe that are its Vaſſals, takes away their Courage, brings on Fear, and creates thoſe Jars and Jealouſies among a People, which makes 'em divide, and become an eaſy Prey to the next bold Invader. I ſay, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is not only the Conſequent of Vice and Debauchery, in reſpect of the thing it ſelf; but much more in reſpect of God, whoſe Juſtice and Holineſs cannot allow, that a wicked People ſhould long be happy or flouriſh in the enjoyment of thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which they have forfeited by their Impieties.</p>
            <p>And to render this applicable to our ſelves, it's too apparent that we are a People fallen into a moſt wretched and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate State, extreamly debauch'd both in Principles and Practices. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God has gone on in a long courſe of Mercy towards this Nation, in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42952:4"/>delivering us; <hi>1ſt,</hi> From Idolatrous Worſhip, (I mean that of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) when others are ſtill blinded with it. <hi>2dly,</hi> In ſaving us from Deſpotick Tyranny and Arbitrary Power, which has prey'd upon ſome of our neighbouring Countries. <hi>3dly,</hi> In reſcuing us from our late Fears and Dangers, (from the ſad apprehenſions of the breaking in of both, I mean, <hi>Idolatrous Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi>) when we had little hope of preſerving our ſelves from either. Tho we have enjoyed theſe Favours, and have pretended too to be ſenſible of them; yet we have behav'd our ſelves under theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances and great Enjoyments, with great Ingratitude, and loud Provocations; ſo that we ſeem by our Deeds, to ſay with the Jews of old, <hi>Jer. 7.10. We are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to do all theſe Abominations.</hi> For where is there any publick ſenſe of our preſervation to effect a change of life, from Profaneneſs to Holineſs, to teſtify we are grateful to our Deliverer? And that we look upon it as the Hand of Heaven that has ſav'd us from our Fears? Should
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42952:4"/>one enquire after the Returns of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Reformation, in reſpect of the main Body of our People, I am too ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they cannot be found or perceived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us: But on the contrary, that we are as lewd, as vile, as vicious as ever; and that in ſome Sins we outſtrip the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of our Fathers, in that the <hi>Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is oppreſt in his Wages,</hi> and we <hi>ſell the Poor for Silver, and the Needy for a pair of Shoes; we make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize one of another, and have no farther any regard to the Publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, than as it's ſubſervient unto our own Private: We have loſt that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Zeal and Affection which every Man ought by Nature to expreſs to the Land of his Nativity.</hi> When I have read ſome Sayings of the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, deſcribing the great Degeneracy of the Jewiſh State, (in that Age of the World) I have been affected with melancholy thoughts, that our Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is but too near a Copy of that foul Pattern.</p>
            <p>But however, if by Melancholy, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42952:5"/>the Cries of the Poor, (which are very loud and clamorous in all our Streets, I am ſure, at leſt, in thoſe that I daily walk) I may be miſtaken; yet the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Debaucheries, which are too noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and all are ſenſible of; all, I mean, that are the Friends of Piety and Vertue; give a juſt cauſe to fear that (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we whiſper to our ſelves Peace and Safety) ſome heavy Judgments from the Juſtice of Heaven are yet approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And ſince nothing but Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can fit us for Mercy, ſince 'tis not our being Proteſtants that can ſcreen us from the Fire of Deſtruction, if we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd only in our Doctrines, but not in our Lives: Therefore it has, and will be the Eternal Honour and Reward of ſome among us, whoſe Names are written in the faireſt Characters in the Book of Life; That God has made them ſenſible of our Degeneracy, and has ſtirr'd them up to undertake this great and noble Work of checking the predominant Vices in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this great City; <hi>Such as profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Lord's Day, the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42952:5"/>Sin of Curſing and Swearing; Houſes of Lewdneſs, and notorious Uncleanneſs, Drunkenneſs, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and the like; by endeavouring the execution of thoſe good Laws which have piouſly been enacted for this End and Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, which at firſt was but like <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Cloud, <hi>no bigger than a Man's hand,</hi> has, by the Divine Bleſſing, ſo enlarg'd it ſelf, that there are now above twenty Societies in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this <hi>Great City,</hi> who have dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to this Good Work. And that it might be made the more manifeſt, <hi>to the terror of evil doers,</hi> it has been reſolv'd, that <hi>Four Sermons a Year,</hi> viz, <hi>One on the Monday next enſuing after the four uſual Quarter-Days,</hi> ſhould be preach'd by ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to ſhew and juſtify the Excellency of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and to encourage to a reſolution in its execution.</p>
            <p>And being requeſted to perform this Office, and alſo to make publick what I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42952:6"/>deliver'd; I have now perform'd both, tho I muſt acknowledg my performance has been by far too mean to recommend ſo glorious a Work.</p>
            <p>And having thus given an Account of the Occaſion of this Diſcourſe; I ſhall only add, That after this Deſign was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by Members of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, (be it ſpoken to their greateſt commendation and praiſe) many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters did join with them, and have been very zealous and vigorous in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting this GREAT END, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt animoſity or jarring about the unhappy difference that lies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us.</hi> May the great and good God in his due time cloſe up our Breaches, and make us all ſenſible, that Real Holineſs is the only Badg of True Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I come to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs my ſelf to you who are Members of thoſe truly honourable Societies for the <hi>Reformation of Manners:</hi> It's a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtance of Divine Love, as well as a Mark of Immortal Honour that the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42952:6"/>Almighty has conferr'd upon you; that he has ſtirr'd up that noble Zeal in you, to endeavour to ſtop the notorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs and Wickedneſs of the Age in which we live.</p>
            <p>It being an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking ſo juſt in its Deſign, ſo commendable in its End, that it carries before it in the plaineſt Characters, <hi>That it came down from God;</hi> and as I hope it's a chearful Inſtance, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our great degeneracy; that the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty has not abandon'd us, as altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible, to Judgment and Ruin: So I pray it may not be the laſt effort of Divine Admonition, trying if we will by theſe Methods be reclaim'd, and render our ſelves capable of the Favours we deſire: Or if it be, That it may not be rendered fruitleſs, either by a general Contempt caſt upon it, and ſo this holy Fire be quench'd by an overflowing general flood of Impiety; or elſe by your growing weary, and cooling in your Zeal, and fainting in your Work, and thereby give occaſion to the Children of Wickedneſs, not only to triumph over you, but over Religion it ſelf, and ſo open
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42952:7"/>a door to thoſe terrible Judgments to ſeize upon us, which we have too much cauſe to fear as the conſequence of our Sins. The deſign of this Diſcourſe is to prevent the latter; and the Juſtice, Honour, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking having been ſo well juſtified by my Reverend Brethren who have gone before me, and whoſe Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are made publick, I thought I could not inſiſt on a more proper Subject, than to recommend the continuance of your Zeal in this ſo good a Work which you have undertaken. And to what has been delivered in the enſuing Pages on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I ſhall only add, That it had been much better you had never ſet about this glorious Work, if you ſhall at laſt fall back and deſiſt from it, ſince nothing can more amate the ſpirit of Piety, or encourage Vice, than your declining and ſinking from a Cauſe which you have ſo openly eſpous'd, and by ſo many Overt-Acts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow'd.</p>
            <p>I write, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> to you conjunctly, and to every particular Member of your Societies ſeverally, and therefore am not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42952:7"/>ſolicitous if any ſhould take an impious occaſion to burleſque the Compariſon, or ridicule the Application of it, taken from ſo low an imployment as that of the Plow; ſince the plainneſs and cloſeneſs of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, as well as the Authority of Him that gave it, cannot diſpleaſe any that are not Atheiſts, or that contemn not the Wiſdom of the Bleſſed Jeſus, the Author of it.</p>
            <p>I acknowledg that ſome do undervalue your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, by urging the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, in allowing ('tis true) <hi>that it's a good Work to ſuppreſs the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſin of Curſing and Swearing, of profaning the Lord's Day, and Houſes of Diſorder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are too nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous about this City. But what's all this to the rooting out of that ſpirit of Selfiſhneſs which is broken looſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, that Bribery and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that has almoſt eaten out the Vitals of the Nation, and which are the blackeſt ſymptoms of approaching De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction?</hi> To which I anſwer; I wiſh there were no occaſion for this irregular
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42952:8"/>Objection, and I daily pray that the Lord may pour forth a publick Spirit upon us, that we may not anſwer the Character which he gives of the laſt days, That Men ſhall be <hi>lovers of themſelves;</hi> but that ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch a generous Love to our dear Countrey may be rais'd up in the Hearts of <hi>all</hi> in Authority, of <hi>all</hi> that are intruſted with the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publick Affairs, that every Man may prefer the publick Intereſt before his own; and that all who wear the badg of Power, may be Perſons anſwering <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Character, <hi>Men of Truth, hating Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince it's allow'd even by the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors, That it's a good Work which you are engag'd in, altho it does not reach all the Ends that they deſire; therefore ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'tis your Honour, your Intereſt, and Duty <hi>to be zealouſly affected in ſo good a thing.</hi> And who knows but that God may be pleas'd, (ſeeing you ſincere and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in his Cauſe, where it lies within the verge of your Power, in ſuppreſſing Vice) to bleſs us in ſuppreſſing, by the Acts of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42952:8"/>his more immediate Providence, thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders which are ſo far out of your reach, which are ſo deſtructive unto our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon National Intereſt? I am ſure it's the only way to avert Judgments, and obtain Mercies, to repreſs Sin: and in doing our duty where we can, we may expect Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and a Divine Hand to help us in thoſe things where we cannot.</p>
            <p>There are other Objectors who urge, That you move in a Sphere that you are not plac'd in, and that you ſtretch your ſelves to a Line beyond your Meaſure, ſince you meddle in what concerns publick Officers. But I hope the enſuing Diſcourſe may help to convince ſuch, that every Man is concern'd in the common cauſe of Vertue, and is liſted as a Soldier to fight the Lord's Battels.</p>
            <p>And as to others who oppoſe you by Scorns and Deriſion; they muſt be ſuch who by their Lives are contrary to the regular Courſes you endeavour to inforce, <hi>whoſe Mouths muſt</hi> (and I hope ſhortly will) <hi>be ſtopt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42952:9"/>
            <p>Since therefore you are engag'd in a field of the greateſt Honour, in a Cauſe ſo beneficial to the Souls of Men hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to their Bodies here; May the great God inſpirit you with Zeal, with Prudence and Induſtry, conſonant to your worthy Deſign. This is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed> Your moſt humble Servant and Welwiſher, <hi>J. Ruſſell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42952:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke ix. 62.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>No Man having put his hand to the Plough, and looking back, is fit for the Kingdom of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Service of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Work of Religion, is a Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of that Honour and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Importance, that it deſerves our moſt ſedulous and conſtant Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and commands a moſt ſtrict adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to it from all its Profeſſors.</p>
            <p>It requires of all thoſe that engage in it, a reſolution to perſevere and go thrô all its Stages, and to hold on to the end of its Journey; and to think nothing dear in compariſon of the Love of their Maſter whom they ſerve, and the Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which is propos'd as their Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For thoſe that draw back at any little Difficulty, and faint in the hour of Trial, and time of Temptation; that have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42952:10"/>not ſpiritual Strength, nor Courage ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to buoy them up againſt ſome Shocks and Oppoſitions which they muſt expect to meet with here in the World: Such Perſons ſhall never, at the great Day of Account, be adjudged faithful, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that incomprehenſible Felicity, which ſhall be the Portion of all thoſe that are truly the Servants of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Religion carries with it ſuch a Grace and Lovelineſs, it appears (even to the common Perſons of the World) with ſuch a Majeſty and Advantage, that he muſt be ſtrongly engaged in the Work of Sin, and cloſely fetter'd, even from his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in the ſlavery of Satan, that never had any Purpoſe or Reſolve to be one of its followers. And I am apt to believe that the far greateſt number of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind have at ſome particular times, in their wiſeſt and moſt conſiderate hours, (being convinced of its Worth and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency) made Reſolutions to ſet about Godlineſs, and to walk in the Paths of Vertue and Religion.</p>
            <p>But when they have found it a Buſineſs of difficulty to quit their Sins, to deny their Luſts; and that the power of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would abridg perhaps their Profit and worldly Advantage, and deny them the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42952:10"/>Excurſions of ſenſual Gratifications; that the way of Piety would ſometimes be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Taunts and Reproaches, and the Thorns and Briars of Affronts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities: Then, like thoſe whom our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour deſcribes <hi>by receiving Seed on ſtony Ground, They are preſently offended,</hi> their Warmth decays, their Zeal grows cold, and they falter and ſtumble, and at laſt deſiſt from their good Reſolutions.</p>
            <p>And tho they have often, on a new fit of Zeal, ſpringing from a reſtored ſenſe of the Excellency, Benefit, and abſolute Neceſſity of a holy Life, renewed their Attempts to proceed in Piety: Yet Satan and the World returning again with ſtrong Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements to the ways of Sin, All their good Purpoſes, like an <hi>evening Cloud,</hi> have vaniſhed away, and they have eaſily return'd to their former Follies, put on their old Fetters, and been baſſled and beat off from all their Religious Undertakings. Like the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when deliver'd out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and purſuing their Journey to the promiſed Land; yet by and by their Appetite (tho they fed upon Angels Food) gave them an hankering for <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons,</hi> and <hi>Cucumbers,</hi> and <hi>Garlick,</hi> and <hi>Onions;</hi> and this (tho an Argument of prodigious Folly, yet) made them in their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42952:11"/>hearts return back to the Houſe of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. So Theſe not being conſtant in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Reſolutions, have look'd back with eyes of Affection on the Pleaſures of Sin, and the Delights of the World, and could not keep up to the juſt tenour of their own good Purpoſes.</p>
            <p>But yet notwithſtanding, being ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps under the ſenſe of Conviction, and the ſtrugglings of Conſcience; in order therefore to ſilence That, and to rebate its edg, they have at laſt fall'n on the ſame Project with thoſe Strangers plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Shalmaneſer</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> in the Cities of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who when Lions were ſent among them, becauſe they feared not the Lord, (2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.13.) in order to remove the Plague, and yet not wholly quit their Idolatry, they made a mixture of Religion, <hi>and ſerv'd God and their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols.</hi> And ſo the Perſons, which fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Character which I have been now deſcribing, will endeavour to reconcile their temporal and ſpiritual Intereſt, and carry on both, mix the Concerns of Time and Eternity, and be moderately religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and moderately wicked: And reply to the inward Arguings and Reproofs of their own Mind, when that checks them for the decays of their former Zeal, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42952:11"/>their ſtate of Lukewarmneſs, and declining their firſt Love:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Why ſhould I attempt a Degree of Holineſs above others, by appearing in a ſingular Zeal in the Cauſe of Religion? And not only concern my ſelf for my own Salvation, but alſo for the Salvation of the Souls of my Neighbours, as if I were made my Brother's Keeper? And perhaps after all, my Zeal may be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than folly, in procuring the Frowns of Superiors, the Loſs of a Cuſtomer, the Coldneſs of a Friend, the Shyneſs of an Acquaintance, becauſe I am now ſtill on the Rebuke, and preſſing the Duties of a rigid Piety on all occaſions. And it may ſavour of Preſumption too, and a ſond conceit of my own Abilities, to attempt the Reformation of the Age, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the World. My Zeal may be too hot, as well as too cold; and Moderation and Self-preſervation too is good in all things. And therefore ſince Piety ought to be mix'd with Prudence, let me not exceed the Rules of Diſcretion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such Returns as theſe to the Calls of Conſcience, are very apt to ſtifie it, when the Will and Affections remain unſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or in a meer moral State. And Men may pleaſe themſelves that all ſhall do well,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42952:12"/>and that Heaven and Eternity may ſtill be gain'd, and Salvation ſecur'd without ſo much ado as ſome Perſons make, and that they themſelves have been more warm than wiſe in the Buſineſs of Religion: And worldly Intereſt, and mundane Deſigns, and ſinful Pleaſures, egging on ſuch thoughts, and urging ſuch falſe and ſinful Arguments; it becomes a ſnare and a ſtumbling-block to multitudes, who ſtill may think their eternal Welfare ſecure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough under the decays and apparent wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of their former Zeal and Holineſs.</p>
            <p>But that ſuch Perſons as theſe are in a dangerous ſtate, and altogether unfit for the Service of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Glory of his Kingdom, and to have their Names inſerted in the Book of Life, our Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us here in this Chapter, by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which he himſelf made on the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of ſome who pretended a great deſire to be his Diſciples. In the <hi>57th</hi> Verſe of this Chapter we read, that a certain Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon appli'd himſelf unto our Lord with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great (ſeeming) Zeal and Affection to his Service, <hi>Lord, I will follow thee whither ſoever thou goeſt.</hi> But on our Lord's telling him, that if he would engage in that Undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he muſt not expect any ſecular advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but rather the contrary; in regard
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42952:12"/>that <hi>tho the Foxes had Holes,</hi> Dens wherein to lodg; <hi>and the Birds of the Air bad Neſts,</hi> places to retreat to, to rooſt in all the night: <hi>Yet he</hi> (tho Lord of all things) here in the World, <hi>had no where to lay his Head;</hi> no Houſe, no Bed, no place of his own to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him; and therefore none were to expect the Advantages of this World, by an entrance into his Service: on which we read no farther, and hear no more of this great Pretender. And calling to another, <hi>v.</hi> 59. <hi>to come and follow him;</hi> he deſires firſt, <hi>that he might have leiſure to bury his Father.</hi> He did not abſolutely refuſe to obey our Lord's Command, but he was willing to procraſtinate and put off the time. And a <hi>3d</hi> ſeeming willing to be his Diſciple, yet would excuſe himſelf from the immediate attendance on his Service; <hi>Lord, I will follow thee; but let me firſt bid them farewel which are at home.</hi> To whom our Lord replies in the words of the Text, <hi>No Man having put his hand to the Plough, and looking back, is fit for the Kingdom of God: i.e.</hi> No Man having engag'd himſelf to my Service, and after turning back to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Concerns, with a regard had firſt to thoſe, <hi>is fit for the Kingdom of God.</hi> The words are allegorical, preſſing a conſtancy to the Service of Chriſt, from the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42952:13"/>of him that tills the Ground: As if our Lord had ſaid, <q>He that holds the Plough, muſt keep to his Buſineſs, not look behind him, or neglect his Work, to trifle about other things that come into his head; if he does, he's unfit for ſuch an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment as requires a conſtant atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on it. So thoſe that enter into my Service, they muſt put on Reſolution, and not make vain and trifling Excuſes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back to the Affairs of the World, but be conſtant and ſedulous, otherwiſe they are not qualified to be my Diſciples; and ſo by conſequence are unfit for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of my Kingdom, which are only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd as the <hi>bleſſed Rewards</hi> of the ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faithful, and conſtantly Laborious.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Text appears to be a ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof levell'd againſt the coldneſs and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent carriage of too many who profeſs to be Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt; who having engag'd themſelves by their <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Vows,</hi> by their <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> by their <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>Pretenſions,</hi> to be his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to eſpouſe the Cauſe of Religion, and Piety, and the Intereſt of Holineſs; and yet after all theſe ſolemn Declarations, by a ſad Tergiverſation return to the World and the things thereof, and to a remiſs and looſe ſtate of Life: And like <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42952:13"/>by <hi>Sodom,</hi> tho they were once, by themer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful hand of convincing Grace, brought out of that ſupine and ſinful Condition in which by Nature they lay, after all thoſe Enlightnings and Lectures of their own Conſciences, do return again like the Dog to his Vomit, to their former Corruptions; or at leaſt with longing Deſires and incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Hearts, look back to that ſtate which will become a Prey to Fire and Brimſtone.</p>
            <p>In ſpeaking therefore on this Subject, I ſhall endeavour to do theſe following things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. To ſhew what it is to put our Hands to the Plough.</item>
               <item>II. To ſhew what it is to look back.</item>
               <item>III. To ſhew the Danger and ſad Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of ſuch a dreadful Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, after we have been engag'd in ſo good a Work; which is, That ſuch Perſons <hi>are not fit for the Kingdom of God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I. For the firſt, What it is to put our Hands to the Plough.</p>
            <p>Since our Lord himſelf is pleas'd to make uſe of this ſo plain and homely a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor; I hope it cannot ſavour of Clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhneſs or Ruſticity to follow his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42952:14"/>and ſince he applies it to thoſe who make a Profeſſion of being his Diſciples, and afterwards withdraw themſelves from his Service, I am ſure it's ſafe and eaſy too to follow ſuch an Expoſitor. The Plough, we know, is an Inſtrument of Husbandry, and they that hold it render the Ground fit for Seed; and this apply'd ſpiritually, ſignifies all thoſe that labour to make the World fit to bring forth fruits of Peace, that ſtrive to reform the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate of Mankind, and to render Mens Hearts capable to receive the Seed of the Word.</p>
            <p>To put our hands to the Plough there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is to declare againſt Sin and the Kingdom of Satan, and to act againſt it in our Station: It is to engage in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Jeſus Chriſt, to endeavour to rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Church fruitful of good Works: 'tis to commence an holy Warfare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtate of Darkneſs, to ſuppreſs Vice, and encourage Holineſs, and to do what in us lies to carry on the Cauſe and Intereſt of Religion. 'Tis with an holy Zeal, and an undauntedneſs of Mind to make oppoſition againſt that torrent of Vice which is breaking in upon the face of the Church; and not only to reform our ſelves, and bring our own Lives into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42952:14"/>to the Divine Pleaſure, but alſo ſtrenuouſly endeavour to reform others; to break up that Soil which is cruſted over with a <hi>Callus</hi> of Sin, and to render it fit for the <hi>ingrafted Word</hi> of the Goſpel to enter. 'Tis, in a word, publickly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſe the Cauſe and Honour of Religion, and to give a check to the growing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Synagogue of Satan.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Church of God, in holy Scripture, is compar'd to a Field, as our Lord himſelf delivers it in that Parable (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.) <hi>of the Wheat and the Tares;</hi> let us conſider how much every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſon is concern'd in the Tillage and Cultivation of it, in order that a bountiful Crop of Righteouſneſs may be brought forth to the Glory of God, and the Salvation of thoſe that labour in this holy Imployment.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Every Man by Nature is a barren Ground, in which only the Seeds of Sin ſpring up and fructify, to the diſhonour of God, and deſtruction of himſelf. And ſince by that infinite Love of God, in giving Jeſus Chriſt, and contracting with us on conditions of Love, he has render'd us capable of bringing forth Fruits meet for Repentance, and reaping, as the effect of ſuch a gracious Harveſt, eternal Life:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42952:15"/>And ſince on our entring into this contract of Peace (I mean, the Covenant of the Goſpel) we have ſworn to our great Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to become his Subjects and Servants, to labour in his Vineyard, to be diligent in his Work; the neglect and breach of which awful Vow, will terminate in Deſtruction: Every one therefore <hi>that is baptized into Chriſt, and has put on Chriſt,</hi> and has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Seal of the Covenant of Grace confirm'd by our Redeemer between God and Us, has put his Hand to the Plough: He has vowed himſelf to be the obedient Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, and has declar'd himſelf an irreconcileable Enemy to all Ungodlineſs; he has promis'd, according to the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.3. <hi>To break up the fallow Ground of his Heart, and not to ſow among Thorns:</hi> and agreeable to <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10.12. <hi>To ſow to himſelf in Righteouſneſs, and thereby to reap Mercy, to break up the fallow Ground, ſince it's time to ſeek the Lord, till he come and rain Righteouſneſs upon him.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Since we are not deſign'd by our great Creator for our ſelves alone, but made for Society, and therefore for the Good and Comfort of others: And ſince in this regard there muſt be a diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Perſons, in reſpect of Superiority and Inferiority, it will be fit to conſider,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42952:15"/>how far we have put our Hand to this good Work in the behalf of others, and who thoſe are that are more particularly concern'd in it. And in doing this, I ſhall briefly conſider the three great Diviſions into which all Men are rank'd, <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Magiſtrates, Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> and ſhew how far each are more than others obliged, and have more immediately ſet their Hand to the Plough.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> A ſtate of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment among Men is appointed by the Light of Nature, as well as by the Law of God: and ſince thoſe that are Governours ought to be Copies and Patterns for the Governed, therefore are Thoſe more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially concern'd in directing others by wholeſom Laws, and juſt Sanctions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Honour of God, and the preſent and future Good of Mankind may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magiſtrates are the Repreſentatives of God;</hi> and if they will not render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves altogether unlike the Majeſty of Heaven, and unfit for, and unworthy of the Character they bear, they muſt more eſpecially <hi>imitate God,</hi> in beſtowing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Encouragements on the Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and by inflicting Puniſhments on the Vicious.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:42952:16"/>
            <p>'Tis their more immediate Duty to enact and execute ſuch Laws, as may be for the ſuppreſſing of Sin, and encouraging Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. And ſince the <hi>higheſt Magiſtrate</hi> in this our happy form of Government, I mean <hi>our Sovereign, (on whoſe Head the Almighty pour down ſtreams of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy)</hi> is obliged by the ſolemnity of an Oath, <hi>to adminiſter Juſtice in Mercy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his People;</hi> I hope all thoſe that are delegated by him to be his Subſtitutes, are, and will be ſo conſcientious in the performance of their Duty, that <hi>That Juſtice</hi> which we owe to God in obeying his Laws, as well as <hi>That</hi> which we owe to Men in preſerving their Right, may be truly and impartially executed, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Rule, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. <hi>For the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well:</hi> Since they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear the Sword in vain, but it muſt be drawn forth by them to eſtabliſh Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, or elſe will be drawn forth on them to ſtrike themſelves into eternal Confuſion.</p>
            <p>And ſince God has called <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> to ſuch an high degree of Honour, that they are his Vice-gerents; they therefore by virtue of the acceptation of their Office, have put their Hands to this good Work,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42952:16"/>being called to be <hi>nurſing Fathers of the Church;</hi> and they bear the Sword of God for this very purpoſe, not <hi>to be a terror unto good Works, but unto the Evil.</hi> And if Any ſhould remain idle and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, or take up this Office for any ſiniſter Ends, to ſerve themſelves ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Publick, to ſit down in ſloth rather than to cultivate the field of God's Church, ſuch Perſons become guilty of a moſt wretched Sacrilege; and have the greateſt Cauſe to fear, that their Swords, which have not been imploy'd in the Cauſe of <hi>Vertue, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> ſhall be turn'd into Darts, and level'd againſt themſelves in the day of eternal Wrath and Vengeance.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> therefore, whoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is to put in execution thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Laws which are enacted for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of Godlineſs, and correction of Sin; Thoſe on the account of their Honour and Office, <hi>have put their Hands to the Plough of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another ſort of Men who are more eſpecially engag'd to this good Work, are <hi>Miniſters;</hi> Thoſe I mean, who are called to preach the Goſpel, and to declare the glad tidings of Reconciliation between God and Men, <hi>by the Man-Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42952:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>We indeed of all Men are more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd, ſince our whole Life ought to be dedicated to this heavenly Work, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for the Converſion and eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mens Immortal Souls; to ſhew them the danger, and the fatal event of an ill-ſpent Life, and a Converſation im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the works of Sin. The Lord has ſhewn us our Dignity and Duty, by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ch. 33.7. <hi>O Son of Man, I have ſet thee a Watchman unto the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>therefore thou ſhalt hear the word at my Mouth, and warn them from me.</hi> And if we who are called to this Sacred Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of <hi>hearing the Word at the Mouth of God,</hi> of having his Oracles committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, who are made <hi>Ambaſſadors of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> to declare <hi>God reconciled to the World</hi> on the Terms of the Goſpel: If we fail of <hi>rebuking, reproving, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, with all Gentleneſs, Meekneſs, and Love;</hi> if we fall under the Character of <hi>idle Shepherds,</hi> neglecting the Flock, thro our want of Zeal in the Cauſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and by <hi>ceaſing to declare the whole Counſels of God for Mens Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> we ſhall find our Account ſo heavy at the great and general Audit of the World, that no Doom will be equal to the Condemnation of ſuch who have thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicated,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42952:17"/>and wretchedly ſlighted their Office and Buſineſs, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.8.</p>
            <p>It's the greateſt Honour we are capable of, in being <hi>brought nigh to God,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Miniſtration of the Word of Life, to be appointed principal La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in raiſing the glorious Building of the Church of Chriſt; to be dignified with the Character of the Legats of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſent in the bleſſed Errand of invit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men to become <hi>reconciled to God.</hi> And as the Reward of ſuch ſhall be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely great, who ſhall with Conſcience and Zeal diſcharge this Duty, <hi>they ſhall ſhine as the Stars in the Firmament for ever and ever:</hi> So the Puniſhment alſo of thoſe that neglect this Duty, ſhall be inconceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably great, <hi>the Blood of Souls ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at their hands, and the Smoke of their Torments ſhall aſcend up for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miniſters</hi> therefore are another ſort of Perſons, who have peculiarly engag'd themſelves to labour in God's Field, to carry on the Deſign and Intereſt of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who have put their hand to the Plough of God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Not only <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> but every <hi>Private Chriſtian,</hi> by the Ties of Humanity, and the Obligations
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42952:18"/>of Religion, is bound to this Work. For ſince the Cauſe of Religion is the common Cauſe of every Member of the Church of Chriſt: Since we are obliged by our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vow, <hi>to fight againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil;</hi> and are bound, by virtue of our Allegiance to our Redeemer, to endeavour to exalt his Kingdom, and to increaſe the number of his Subjects: Every Man therefore is concern'd for his Neighbour, is obliged for his Brother, to do what is poſſible to pluck him out of the Power of Satan, and to bring him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtate of Mercy through obedience to Jeſus Chriſt. And ſince there's a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Love and natural Compaſſion in all Mankind, which is wonderfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and ſanctified by Grace; ſo that every one that comes to conſider the worth of his own immortal Soul, will have a concern of Charity for the Soul of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Therefore we ought to be (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we ſhall be if we are our ſelves rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate) ſolicitous for the Salvation of all Mankind; and every Man will become a friendly Monitor unto his Neighbour, and will come to him in <hi>Prudence,</hi> in <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Secrecy,</hi> if he ſee him negligent in the important Concern of his eternal Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and will requeſt him to beware of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42952:18"/>his heedleſs Condition; that he'd take ſome cognizance of the way in which he is walking, whither it tends, and where 'twill end; that he'd not ruſh into the Gulph of everlaſting Deſtruction thro' folly and incogitancy, but conſider the <hi>Weight of Eternity, the Worth of his Soul, and the Love of God, and the Value of Heaven,</hi> and <hi>the dreadful State of Eternal Vengeance;</hi> and that he'd labour earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obtain the one, and avoid the other. And this is a Duty which we owe to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, both as we are of the ſame Nature, and as we are commanded by the Divine Word, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer Sin upon him.</hi> And ſo St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb. 3.13. <hi>Exhort one another daily, while it is called, To day: And</hi> (in another place) <hi>let us provoke one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to Love, and to good Works.</hi> And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, We are not only to <hi>Perſwade</hi> our Neighbours, and to uſe all the Methods of Love and Kindneſs to engage them to their Duty; but alſo, ſince ſome are ſo abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably vicious, that nothing but the terror and puniſhment of the Magiſtrate can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from the open violation of the Law of God; therefore it's the Duty of every Man to detect <hi>Such</hi> unto the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that where the Force of Perſwaſion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42952:19"/>cannot prevail, there the Power of the Sword may reſtrain. And that 'tis our Duty thus to diſcover all ſuch Perſons who are the <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>Notorious</hi> Oppoſers of Piety, and endeavour to bring upon them legal Inflictions; not only appears from the nature of the thing, but alſo from a conſideration of that general Duty which lies upon us, to labour for the ſupport of the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſtruction of the Power of <hi>Satan.</hi> And ſince there are Many ſo deplorably wicked, that the whole Bent and Stream of their Converſation is ſcandalous and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, offenſive to <hi>God,</hi> deſtructive to <hi>Themſelves,</hi> and pernicious to <hi>Others:</hi> Therefore every Man is bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>God,</hi> and in Honour to <hi>Vertue,</hi> to make ſuch Perſons publick Examples, by labouring to inflict thoſe Penalties upon them, which our good and wholſom Laws have determined.</p>
            <p>'Tis our great happineſs, that we live under a Government where Iniquity is ſo far from being <hi>eſtabliſhed by a Law,</hi> or ſo much as left Neutral, that 'tis not only for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, but alſo puniſhed. But our Laws are nothing but dead Letters, and Juſtice holds <hi>but a wooden Sword</hi> without execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for 'tis that which is the Life of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42952:19"/>Law it ſelf, and the Honour of that People which enjoy ſuch wholeſom Conſtitutions. And ſince <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> to whom the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Laws are committed, cannot do it, without information of the <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Crimes</hi> of Offenders; therefore 'tis every Man's Duty, as he tenders the Honour of God, and the Glory of the Goſpel, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Church, and the Good of the Weal-Publick, and as <hi>He would not be a partaker of other Mens Sins</hi> in hiding and concealing them, to detect ſuch as openly and commonly affront the Majeſty of God, and the Authority of Man, by notorious Vices, and thoſe ſcandalous Impieties which make us ſtink in the Noſtrils of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and bring down his Plagues and Judgments upon us.</p>
            <p>But this Point having been formerly ſo well prov'd in this place, and on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in former Diſcourſes, I ſhall therefore proceed towards a concluſion of the firſt head of the Text, That <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> by their Power, <hi>Miniſters</hi> by their Office, and every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> by his Character as ſuch, <hi>has put his Hand to the Plough of God,</hi> has given in his Name as a Labourer in the Field of the Church of Chriſt, in order to root out the Weeds of Impiety, and to ſow and cheriſh the good Seed of Grace, that we
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42952:20"/>may all grow up to Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this, more particularly God has ſtirr'd up the Hearts of <hi>Some</hi> in and about this <hi>Great City,</hi> whoſe Numbers God of his Mercy increaſe, and whoſe Zeal God of his Goodneſs augment, who have united themſelves in Religious Fraternities, for the more effectual carrying on of <hi>This Glorious and never to be enough commended Work, of giving a check to Vice, and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (if poſſible) the corrupt and depraved Manners</hi> of the unhappy <hi>Age</hi> in which we <hi>live.</hi> And <hi>You</hi> who are enter'd into this Noble Deſign, whoſe Hearts God has more eſpecially touch'd with a ſenſe of your Duty, <hi>You</hi> have in a more than ordinary manner <hi>put your hand to the Plough.</hi> And to encourage you in it, I ſhall truly affirm that this Work, and the Undertakers of it, are the great ſpringing Glory of our Church, and a comfortable Teſtimony that God has not utterly left us off to Judgment.</p>
            <p>This is a Deſign worthy of <hi>Men,</hi> as we are the Image of God; and worthy of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as we are the Diſciples of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. 'Tis the Cauſe of <hi>God</hi> that you have undertaken, in oppoſition to the <hi>Devil;</hi> and the Cauſe of <hi>Vertue,</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to <hi>Vice;</hi> and of <hi>Religion,</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42952:20"/>to <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> 'Tis an Enterprize that is every way praiſe-worthy; and I may ſpeak it with a ſufficient degree of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>'Tis worthy of God to own, and Men to proſecute;</hi> and I hope it's carried on by Means that are agreeable unto the noble End which it deſigns. <hi>And certainly no Man can oppoſe it, or become an Enemy unto it, that does not firſt by his own Life render himſelf obnoxious to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, my <hi>Brethren,</hi> if after you have thus begun in a Divine Work, and have increas'd your Numbers, and diffus'd your Deſign throughout the Parts of this mighty City; and you have ſeen many good Fruits of theſe your Endeavours, In cleanſing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Augean</hi> Stables of Luſt and Filthineſs; In making many, who made no conſcience of profaning the Name of God, to ſet a bar before their Lips; In repreſſing the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders which are too frequently commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the Lord's Day; And (in charity one may hope) of bringing ſeveral to a ſenſe of their Sin, and to a ſincere Repentance, and to bleſs the Almighty for this your Undertaking: Now if after all this, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſhould become ſo miſchievouſly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful as to ſtifle your Zeal, and to baffle you in your Work by the little Mocks, Scoffs, and Taunts of thoſe that are his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42952:21"/>If you faint at the oppoſition that you muſt expect to meet with from the <hi>Frowns</hi> of Some, and the <hi>Threats</hi> of Others: If this beat you out of the Field into which you have entred in order to work: It would not only be a ſad <hi>Omen</hi> of your own Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Decay, but be alſo a great Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto Others; and would give the greateſt blow unto the Cauſe of Religion, by adding the Trophies and Enſigns of Succeſs, to the black Triumphs of the Prince of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>But this I ſhall farther inſiſt on in the next part of the Text, which is,</p>
            <p n="2">II. To ſhew what 'tis <hi>to look back.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the putting our Hand to the Plough intends the ingaging our ſelves in the Cauſe and Intereſt of Holineſs, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the repreſſing of Sin, and propagation of Piety; ſo to <hi>look back</hi> ſignifies, a with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing our Affections and Endeavours from it, and a relinquiſhing this ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and commendable an Enterprize.</p>
            <p>And in ſpeaking of this, I ſhall briefly take notice, <hi>1ſt,</hi> of the <hi>Perſons;</hi> and <hi>2dly,</hi> Of the <hi>Temptations</hi> inducing to this ſinful Retroſpection.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place, as to <hi>the Perſons;</hi> I cannot but briefly remark with a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42952:21"/>Reflection, that not only vaſt Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who are engag'd by the awful Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Baptiſm, have no more ſenſe of their Duty and Intereſt, than if they had been brought up in a Land of Darkneſs. Not only great Multitudes hear the Goſpel every day, and themſelves alſo read the Holy Scriptures, and yet they are to 'em as <hi>a Book ſeal'd;</hi> they neither feel, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Power and Life.</p>
            <p>But alſo there are others, who have had a ſight and ſenſe of their Duty, have been under Convictions, and taken up Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for Heaven and Eternity; and yet all their Purpoſes, like <hi>Ephraim</hi>'s Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, have been but as <hi>a morning Dew,</hi> which is preſently conſum'd with the heat of the next approaching Temptation. And this is very ſadly <hi>to look back,</hi> after we have <hi>ſet our Hands to the Plough:</hi> when we have felt the warmings of the Divine Spirit in our Hearts, the incubations of the Holy Ghoſt brooding on our Souls, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to bring forth the Image of God in a ſtate of renewed Holineſs; when we have made ſome advances in Piety, and have <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the Spirit,</hi> yet after all <hi>to end in the Fleſh;</hi> this is miſerably <hi>to look back</hi> from our Employment, and ſolemn En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:42952:22"/>
            <p>But <hi>2dly,</hi> to carry on my Application.</p>
            <p>You, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who have promis'd to become the Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, not only by the Vow of your Baptiſm, but alſo by the Rules of thoſe Religious Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into which you are engag'd, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage one another <hi>to walk as becomes the Goſpel,</hi> and to declare your ſelves the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents to Vice and Ungodlineſs, and to repreſs Profanation, Debauchery, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, within your ſphere and knowledg, by endeavouring to give Life and Vigour to thoſe good Laws, which our Pious Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators have eſtabliſh'd for this End: Conſider, you have put your Hand to the Plough of God; for 'tis his Cauſe that you are engag'd in; and if upon the account of ſome little oppoſition, you withdraw your Aſſiſtance, or ſtop in your Duty, this is the <hi>looking back</hi> here intimated in the Text.</p>
            <p>I beg, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I may not be miſtaken, as if I was afraid you were weary of that good Work which you have ſet your Hands unto, and were about to relinquiſh it; my Diſcourſe proceeds from another Deſign, namely, That by ſhewing the great Miſchief which muſt attend your forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Cauſe, I might the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally recommend it to your <hi>Selves,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42952:22"/>
               <hi>Others</hi> to engage in it, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage your Zeal to all the prudential and vigorous Methods which are needful for its Proſecution.</p>
            <p>But yet, ſince 'tis not impoſſible, but ſome who have ſet their Hands to this good Work may look back, may flag in their Diligence, and cool in their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I ſhall briefly take notice of ſome of the Temptations tending to it; and theſe fall under one or the other of theſe 3 Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st.</hi> Fear. <hi>2dly.</hi> Shame. <hi>3dly.</hi> Sloth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Fear. When a Perſon that has not firſt ſat down and <hi>counted the Coſt,</hi> what it will ſtand him in to be the Soldier of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and what degree of Valour and holy Reſolution it requires to fight in this glorious Cauſe, and to labour in this Work; that he muſt be ſincere and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, not afraid of the Reproaches of the <hi>Small,</hi> or the Frowns of the <hi>Great,</hi> or any diminution of his temporal Intereſt: when ſuch a Perſon finds that the Cauſe he has undertook may eclipſe his Profit, and that there is indeed greater Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than he expected; then he begins to faint, and to chill in his Warmth, and to find excuſes for his Receſſion. But let ſuch conſider, that St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>That the Fearful, as well as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving, ſhall have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42952:23"/>their part in the Lake which burns with Fire and Brimſtone,</hi> Rev. 21.8. i. e. Such who faint in the ſpiritual Warfare, and have not courage enough to ſtand up for the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt, in oppoſition to the Conveniencies and Friendſhips of the World, ſuch are unfit for the Kingdom of God. And as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>That the fear of Man bringeth a Snare,</hi> Prov. 29.25. a Snare on the Conſcience, and an intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hindrance to religious Duties; ſo He that ventures upon the diſpleaſure of God rather than Man, or whom ſordid appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of worldly loſs, or the breach of carnal Friendſhip, or the browbeatings of the Powerful, can beat off from his Work; ſuch a Perſon does hereby render himſelf unfit for that bleſſed Sentence, of <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant, enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord.</hi> For he that cannot ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himſelf on the Cauſe of Chriſt Jeſus, and whoſe Faith is too feeble to ſhore him up from ſinking under the fear of Men; ſuch a Perſon is a miſerable Bondman to the World, how fair ſoever his pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be to Regeneration and Holineſs of Life. <hi>But, Beloved,</hi> I believe and hope <hi>better things of you, and things that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> a zeal of Sincerity, and a vigorous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of your glorious Undertaking.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:42952:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Shame is another Temptation to induce Men to look back.</p>
            <p>It has been the chiefeſt Policy of Satan, ever ſince God has (in wonderful Mercy unto his Church) been pleas'd to ſtop the violence of his Rage and Perſecution, to oppoſe Religion by Scoffs and Mockings at thoſe that will not ſtill remain his Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals. And our Age and Nation has been ſo unhappily exerciſed by this ſtratagem of Hell, that one would be tempted to think, that the Prophecy of St. <hi>Peter</hi> look'd at theſe Days, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Knowing this, that there ſhall come in the laſt days Scoffers, walking after their own Luſts.</hi> For how has Holineſs of Life been ridicul'd, and the Power of Godlineſs, and the Life of the the Spirit, and a ſtate of Converſion and Regeneration, been made the ſubject of impious Deriſion, and ſcornful Reproach, inſomuch, that Some have been even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to own themſelves ſo good as they really were, for fear that ſome name of Ignominy and Contempt would be caſt upon them?</p>
            <p>And indeed I do not find any Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on greater than this, to balk you in the way of your vertuous procedure. But to counterpoiſe this, remember that you are engag'd to own the Cauſe of a Crucified
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42952:24"/>Jeſus, of him that <hi>was number'd among the Tranſgreſſors, and who endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame;</hi> and if you have not conſtancy enough to bear a little Reproach for the ſake of our great Maſter, and to be contented to undergo the name of <hi>Informers,</hi> and <hi>buſy Fellows,</hi> or ſuch who make a noiſe to get your ſelves a Name; if you cannot patiently endure the Reproaches of the Agents of Hell, and the Lies and Scandals they will caſt at your Doors; if you faint at this Trial (as <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides</hi> ſays) <hi>your Strength is ſmall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this ſhould induce any Member to look back, let him be afraid of being hereby made unfit for the Kingdom of God: for remember what our Lord tells us, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be aſham'd of me, and of my Words, in this adulterous and ſinful Generation, of him alſo ſhall the Son of Man be aſham'd, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father, with the Holy Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly. Sloth</hi> may be another inducement to look back: For He that applies himſelf to this good Work with that fitneſs which it requires, ought to be a Perſon of <hi>Induſtry</hi> and <hi>Diligence,</hi> he muſt dedicate ſome part of his time for fighting the Lord's Battels againſt the publick <hi>Goliahs</hi> of the Armies of Hell; he ought to appear perſonally in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42952:24"/>the Cauſe that he has undertook, and not think it enough that he has been a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributor towards the Charge of this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fabrick of Reformation.</p>
            <p>For tho I do not queſtion but that every Penny that's beſtowed on this Account, is as true Charity, <hi>as feeding the Hungry,</hi> or <hi>clothing the Naked,</hi> and has alſo in it ſomething of an excellency far beyond it, as a Compaſſion on Mens Immortal Souls does exceed the pity that's expreſt to their Bodies; yet I cannot chuſe but deliver my Judgment in this matter, altho it ſhould happen to be contrary to the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſome here preſent, <hi>That the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Member of theſe Societies, who by a perſonal endeavour labours in this Work, who ſacrifices his Time and Pains at this Altar, his Offering is greater, and he caſts in more to his</hi> Corban, <hi>than they who of their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance beſtow many Pounds yearly:</hi> Not that I blame, no, I commend the <hi>One,</hi> but I highly praiſe and extol the <hi>Other;</hi> and I do it in order to give all poſſible Encouragement to a perſonal, zealous, and avowed Proſecution of this Heroick Undertaking.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To conclude this Point, I ſhall add a word to encourage to an exemplary Holineſs of Life.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:42952:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And this, if You who have undertaken to be the Patrons of Vertue, and ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Piety, ſhall fail in; if you ſhall ſink down from your exalted Poſt, to the Temptations of the World, and be taken in the ſnares of Vice and Diſhoneſty, this will be ſuch a Tergiverſation, as muſt not only be ſatal to your ſelves, but alſo to your Deſign; and will caſt the blackeſt Cloud on the honeſt and ſincere endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of thoſe that are join'd with you. It will open a Door to all the foul Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches that Hell can invent, and the Agents thereof inject upon you; which will not only fall with the greateſt weight on the Heads of the Guilty, but will alſo affect thoſe that are Innocent.</p>
            <p>It therefore becomes every one that is engag'd in this Holy Work, to <hi>walk cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, not as Fools, but as Wiſe,</hi> conſidering the Eagle Eyes of all your Adverſaries await your ſteps; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can give them ſuch an occaſion of impious Joy, as your ſtumbling and faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering at the ſame Stones which you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to remove: and this will indeed be the worſt ſort of looking back which poſſibly you can commit. <hi>Be therefore wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves:</hi> And as glorious Deſigns muſt be managed with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42952:25"/>the higheſt <hi>Prudence</hi> in order to ſecure 'em from the reproaches of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; ſo let this be attended with a <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Circumſpection</hi> agreeable to it, ſuch as your Adverſaries cannot gainſay or reſiſt. And to obtain this, be inſtant in Prayer, that That <hi>Great God,</hi> whoſe Cauſe you have undertaken, would give a particular Bleſſing, in directing every Member ſo to walk, that you may be <hi>blameleſs and harmleſs, the Sons of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebuke, in the midſt of a perverſe and crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Generation, among whom ye ſhine as Lights in the World,</hi> and as Patterns of Piety, Humility, and Meekneſs, and every thing that is praiſe-worthy.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I come now to the laſt part of the Text, which is, to ſhew the Danger and ſad Conſequence of ſuch a dreadful Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, after we have been engag'd in ſo good an Employment, Which is, <hi>that ſuch Perſons who look back, are not fit for the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having already in my former Diſcourſe, given frequent hints of this, I ſhall be very brief on this Topick, that I may oppreſs your Patience no longer. In order to which, I will not inlarge what is here meant by the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:42952:26"/>in regard the ſenſe is obvious to every Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, it ſignifying the Enjoyment of all that Happineſs which Jeſus has purchaſed, and is gone into Heaven to prepare for his Church and People. And as thoſe who are not fit for the Glories of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, do not only miſs of Happineſs, but fall into Miſery; ſo <hi>That</hi> ſhews ſomething more than the loſs of Heaven, there's an implication of the Puniſhment of Hell.</p>
            <p>The loſs therefore of Eternal Life, and the Condemnation to everlaſting Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, muſt ſtrike Terror one very one that conſiders the worth of his never-dying Soul, and what 'tis to undergo the Wrath of God for ever and ever. But yet this muſt kindle a greater fire of Torment in the Conſciences of <hi>Some,</hi> than of <hi>Others:</hi> for he that never had the Means of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or on whom they never came with Power and Efficacy, the Reflections of <hi>Such</hi> can never be ſo bitter, ſo ſharp, and ſtinging, as of <hi>Thoſe</hi> who have had the clearer diſcoveries of Divine Light and Love. And therefore for ſuch <hi>who have been made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted the good Word of God, and the Powers of the World to come, if They fall away, it's not only impoſſible to renew them again by Repentance,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42952:26"/>to render their Condemnation half ſo tolerable as of thoſe who had never thoſe participations.</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore, <hi>You</hi> who have put <hi>your Hands to the Spiritual Plough,</hi> in order to cultivate both your ſelves and others; if you, after both the Vow of your Baptiſm, inward Conviction, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion, and a more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obliging your ſelves to the Service of Chriſt Jeſus; If <hi>You</hi> look back, of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the World, you are moſt unfit for the glorious Kingdom. <hi>The Backſlider in Heart</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>ſhall be filled with his own Ways,</hi> Prov. 14.14. i. e. ſhall reap the fruits of his own Folly. But as I hope you have well conſider'd the weight of the Work which you have undertook, ſo I truſt your Perſeverance in it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Pattern to ſucceeding Times, and other Places. And that your Zeal, your Wiſdom, and Prudence, will be ſtill more and more Illuſtrious, and fit you for the love of all good Men here, and for great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than ordinary degrees of Glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. And agreeable hereunto this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation ſhall ſhut up my Diſcourſe, That as he that looks back is <hi>unfit,</hi> ſo he that goes on and proſecutes his Work, that has an eye of Reſolution, looking
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42952:27"/>forward on his Duty, ſuch a Perſon is thro' Jeſus Chriſt <hi>fit</hi> for the Favour and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. And your being <hi>Such,</hi> will add to your Crown another day, and will advance you above the common Bleſſing of Heaven, and of eternal Life; your Zeal and Conſtancy will be rewarded with a double Portion of everlaſting Glory. For the God that you ſerve, <hi>is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous to forget your Works and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of Love,</hi> but will be a Maſter of the greateſt bounty, in liberally requiting all your diligent and faithful Services.</p>
            <p>And that you may All be ſet down in the number of thoſe that have endured to the End, and have finiſhed your Work with Joy and Faithfulneſs: This the Almighty grant, by the Aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit, thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42952:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
